A Guide to the George Cruikshank Collection, 1825-1872
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
George Cruikshank Collection 1825-1872
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
3833
This collection consists of 88 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Fitzgerald Bemis, November 27, 1951.
Scope and Content Information
Correspondents include: publishers D. Bogue and Charles Tilt, and authors George Mills ( Beggar's Benison) and John Wight ( Humbug for the Million)
Contents List
- Correspondence
  - John Wright to Cruikshank. Contains proposal for new work - Humbug for the Millions. ca. 1825/1833, ALS (Box 1)
  - Cruikshank to [?]; sending one dozen (sic) caricatures, 6 Exhibition Extraordinary in the Horticultural Rooms and 7 Devil Among Bankers. With rough sketches on verso. 1827 Feb. 22, ALS (Box 1)
  - Fragment, in unidentified hand, of criticism of Cruikshank's Omnibus No. VI. [1841] (Box 1)
  - [?] to Cruikshank. Fragment of a letter. Sketches on back. 1841 Feb. 9 (Box 1)
  - J. L. Gardner to Cruikshank. Wants Cruikshank to do illustrations for his (Gardner's) poems Evil Spirits. Verso has sketches and a draft of Cruikshank's reply stating that he will be happy to undertake the work. 1843 Dec. 14, ALS (Box 1)
  - P. D. Bradish to Cruikshank. Refers to "glorious improvement" of train travel over that of coach. Some account of political situation in Manchester. 1844 June 8, ALS (Box 1)
  - J. W. Hinckley to Cruikshank. Letter of thanks. Sketch of elephant on verso. 1847 Jan. 11, ALS (Box 1)
  - John Scollier to Cruikshank. Refers to success of Cruikshank's The Bottle and suggests that he do a sequel-a series on the subject The Drunkard Reclaimed. With pencil sketches on verso. 1847 Dec. 10, ALS (Box 1)
  - H. Solomon to Cruikshank. Requests him to preside at an entertainment of readings from English poets. The meeting sponsored by the Jews and General Mechanics Athenaeum. Small sketch on letter. 1849 March 5, ALS (Box 1)
  - W. F. Tillwood to Cruikshank. Asks for an appointment in order to discuss an etching for a book. 1849 Aug. 6, ALS (Box 1)
  - C. P. Newcombe to Cruikshank. Requesting that he preside at a meeting-the annual festival of the Coventry Temperance Society. [Sketches on page 1 & 4]. 1849 Aug. 27, ALS (Box 1)
  - Thomas Marshall to Cruikshank requesting his patronage and presence at a celebration in honor of the opening of both sections of the Sheffield Athenaeum & Mechanics Institution for public use. [Sketches on verso.] 1849 Oct. 12, ALS (Box 1)
  - Cruikshank. To [?]. Incomplete letter regarding an invitation. Verso has written plan for a series of drawings. 1850 Feb. 16, AL (Box 1)
  - Cruikshank to his publisher. Regarding a second edition of The Betting Book and suggesting a few altercations. 1852 Aug. 18, ALS (Box 1)
  - T. C. Prebble to Cruikshank. Requests contribution to Temperance Fund list. Jottings and sketches. 1853 June 6, ALS (Box 1)
  - T. Brown to Cruikshank; receipt for rent. Also a temperance note by Cruikshank and sketches, including sketch for "Fairy Ring". 1855 Sept. 29, ALS (Box 1)
  - Harrison Penney to Cruikshank. Requests autograph. Sketch on verso. 1856 Dec. 10, ALS (Box 1)
  - Draft of a letter Cruikshank to [?] concerning illustrations. On same leaf a sketch of Falstaff; and of the Captain of Knockaunder for Scott's Tales of My Landlord. 1857 March 14 (Box 1)
  - George W. McGee to Cruikshank. Asks Cruikshank to preside at a meeting. Sketches on verso. 1857 June 12, ALS (Box 1)
  - George Mills [author of The Beggar's Benison] to Cruikshank. Thanks Cruikshank for letter of sympathy on occasion of the death of Mill's brother and urging Cruikshank to come for a visit to Glasgow. 1859 June 6, ALS (Box 1)
  - Draft of a letter Cruikshank to [?], re Volunteers. Sketch on verso. 1865 May 23 (Box 1)
  - John R. Shingleton to Cruikshank enclosing a bill. On verso Cruikshank notes on volunteers and a sketch. 1866 July 27, ANS (Box 1)
  - J. M. Mathews to Cruikshank. Confirming reservations of a room. With sketch on verso. 1867 Jan. 8, ALS (Box 1)
  - W. H. Benyon-Winsor to Cruikshank. In regard to a studio. Sketch of horse on verso. 1870 Feb. 10, ALS (Box 1)
  - Edwin Pearson to Cruikshank. Requesting a book in order to finish a block for illustration Note on back in Cruikshank's hand referring to etchings made for German Popular Stories. Also a sketch. 1870 April 21, ALS (Box 1)
  - Edward Weir (for A.F.A. Coy) to J. Coutts. Regarding Cruikshank's Shakespearean prints for view lanterns. On back is a Cruikshank note acknowledging gifts-compliments author on his introduction to first present. Also small sketches. 1872 Nov. 9, ALS (Box 1)
  - D. Bogue to George Cruikshank re second edition of The Bottle. n.d., ALS (Box 1)
  - List of engagements in Cruikshank's autograph. Sketches on small leaf. n.d. (Box 1)
  - Plan showing location of Cruikshank's house with various lists on back. On same leaf various small sketches, all by Cruikshank. n.d. (Box 1)
  - Envelope with draft of a letter in Cruikshank's autograph on verso and sketch of head. n.d. (Box 1)
  - Draft of note in Cruikshank's autograph about his Volunteer service, 2 p. Also three small sketches. n.d. (Box 1)
  - Scrap of paper with penciled accounts and small drawings. n.d. (Box 1)
  - Fragment of draft of a letter. Two small sketches on same leaf. n.d. (Box 1)
  - Draft note about publishing rights with drawing of horses head on verso. n.d. (Box 1)
  - William Loaden to Cruikshank with two pencil drawings on verso. n.d., Incomplete ANS (Box 1)
  - Charles Tilt to Cruikshank with drawings on verso. n.d., ANS (Box 1)
  - Cruikshank to George Mills, thanking him and his brother for discounting a bill. With two sketches. n.d., ALS (Box 1)
  - Fragment of note in Cruikshank's hand with small sketch on back. n.d. (Box 1)
  - Fragment of letter to a Miss Widdeson in unidentified autograph. Sketches on verso. n.d. (Box 1)
  - Envelope addressed to Cruikshank with sketch on verso. n.d. (Box 1)
- Drawings n.d., 49 sketches on 46 sheets, some mounted (Box 1)
  Various undated sketches by Cruikshank, sixteen of which were apparently done for John Wight's Humbug for the Million.